<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nicole A. Vargas-Fuentes</title>
    <link>https://nvargasf.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nvargasf.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Nicole A. Vargas-Fuentes</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 14:30:42 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nvargasf.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Nicole A. Vargas-Fuentes</title>
      <link>https://nvargasf.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heritage Lexical Writing</title>
      <link>https://nvargasf.github.io/project/heritage-lexical-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 14:30:42 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nvargasf.github.io/project/heritage-lexical-writing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emotion and Bilingualism</title>
      <link>https://nvargasf.github.io/project/emotion-and-bilingualism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 13:22:40 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nvargasf.github.io/project/emotion-and-bilingualism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Typically, bilinguals report different emotional experiences across their languages with their native language (L1) deemed as more emotional. However, this is not the case for all bilingual populations since variation in the bilingual experience (e.g., age of acquisition, dominance, proficiency, exposure, etc.) can influence the degree of emotionality. The objective of this project is to start to discern which of these aspects have greater influence on emotionality. Primarily we are interested in studying emotionality in heritage speakers since they, as a bilingual population, they have unique characteristics. Usually, heritage speakers start learning their L1 (e.g., Spanish) at home, but later acquire and become more dominant in the majority societal language (e.g., English). The question is whether the emotionality associated with L1 is transferred during the language dominance shift or is it shared between both languages? To investigate this emotion-language relationship, we are conducting a series of studies with 3 different paradigms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Emotional Carryover effect:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study is to assess (1) how bilinguals process emotional words in their non-native language, (2) how emotional words are stored and retrieve in memory, and (3) how the processing of emotional word can benefit or hinder the processing and recall of preceding/following neutral words. Research has shown that emotional stimuli have recall advantage over neutrals stimuli due to their higher arousal levels and their deep automatic processing; this advantage is referred to as the emotion-memory effect. We are looking at whether that advantage carries over to preceding and subsequent stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Color Discrimination task:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study also looks at the emotion-memory effect but in a high vs low cognitive task. We want to know if the emotional valence of words has a bigger effect in recall when the ongoing task creates a high or low cognitive load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Emotional Face-word Stroop task:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This study is part of an ongoing Honors Thesis project&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study aims to investigate the Stroop task effect in an emotional face-word paradigm. Specifically, this study looks at whether the effect is stronger within Mandarin Heritage speakers or Chinese international students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
